Andrea Esparza

Houston, TX | 915-588-9734 | acesparza05@gmail.com LinkedIn | Github | Bloq | Portfolio

Software Engineer | Full Stack Developer

I am a passionate and motivated individual seeking a career as a software engineer. At Flatiron School, I gained experience with JavaScript, React, Ruby, and Rails. My five years as a high school teacher and four years as a board member for a national sports organization taught me how to be relentlessly organized, an effective collaborator, and extremely adaptable.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Ruby, Rails, JavaScript, React, HTML, CSS, PostgreSQL

TECHNICAL PROJECTS

Student-Teacher Resource - Demo | Github

App that allows students to easily find their schedules and assignments and allows teachers to keep track of their students' information

- Designed the full stack application using Ruby/Rails and React/JavaScript
- Centralized information to improve teacher and student organization
- Utilized BCrypt to ensure users can create accounts and store their information safely

Wanderlust - Demo | Github

App for travelers to explore what others have to say about the countries they want to visit and post reviews for other travelers

- Co-developed an application using a JavaScript/React frontend and Ruby/Rails backend
- Applied full CRUD capabilities allowing authorized users to add, edit, delete their reviews
- Implemented a search bar for users to filter the destination list using React state variables

Art Gallery - Demo | Github (front end) | Github (back end)

Simulates what it's like to walk through an art gallery and allows artists to add their own pieces

- Collaborated to design a full stack application using Ruby/Sinatra and React/JavaScript
- Utilized RESTful routing to connect artists to their art on the frontend
- Styled the application using Tailwind CSS

EXPERIENCE

Navarro Early College High School

AUG 2017 - MAY 2022

Math Teacher and Soccer Coach

Austin, TX

- Developed a year-long geometry team curriculum, including lesson plans and assessments
- Collaborated with 12 teachers in math department to align our curriculum vertically
- Assessed how each class engaged with the content in real time and adjusted lessons accordingly
- Scheduled, planned, and conducted soccer practices that focused on player development

Premier Ultimate League

SEP 2018 - MAR 2022

Board of Directors Member

Austin, TX

- Co-founded a semi-professional ultimate frisbee team and the league it plays in
- Led the board of directors committee that assembled a rulebook for all 300 players in the league

EDUCATION

Flatiron School JUN 2022 - OCT 2022

Full Stack Development - Ruby, Rails, JavaScript, React

University of Texas at Austin

JAN 2013 - MAY 2017

Bachelor of Science in Mathematics